Guide to the Eugenia Flatow Papers 1940-2011 (bulk 1963-2005) MS 3175
New-York Historical Society
- Series IV. Organizational Records, 1961-2010 (bulk 1970s-1990s)
  - Subseries IV.E. New York-New Jersey Harbor Estuary Program (HEP), 1980-2002
    - Habitat Maps (2 Folders), circa 1993-1997 (Offsite-box 33, Folder 11-12)
      This file contains maps and other documentation used by the Habitat Workgroup of the New York/New Jersey Harbor Estuary Program.
    - Habitat Workgroup (8 Folders), 1997-2003 (Offsite-box 33, Folder 13-20)
    - Harbor Health/Human Health, 2002 (Offsite-box 34, Folder 1)
    - HEP Outreach, 1989-1997 (Offsite-box 34, Folder 2)
      This file contains several issues of The Tidal Exchange, the newsletter of the NY/NJ Harbor Estuary Program.
    - Hudson River Estuary Management Program: Strategy for the Development of a Fifteen Year Management Program, 1988 (Offsite-box 34, Folder 3)
    - The Hudson-Raritan: State of The Estuary, 1987 (Offsite-box 34, Folder 4)
    - Hudson/Raritan Estuary: Issues, Resources, Status, and Management, 1988 (Offsite-box 34, Folder 5)
    - Landfills, 1997-1998 (Offsite-box 34, Folder 6)
    - Management Plan (CCMP), 1996 (Offsite-box 34, Folder 7)
    - Managing the Estuary; Hudson River Symposium, 1988 (Offsite-box 34, Folder 8)
    - Minutes (5 Folders), 1988-1991 (Offsite-box 34, Folder 9-13)
    - National Estuary Program, New York - New Jersey Harbor, 1987 (Offsite-box 34, Folder 14)
    - New York Dredged Material Disposal Alternatives Workshop, 1977 (Offsite-box 34, Folder 15)
    - New York Harbor Collection and Removal of Drift Project, 1975 (Offsite-box 34, Folder 16)
    - NY/NJ Harbor Estuary Program Citizens Advisory Committee (3 Folders), circa 1990-2002 (Offsite-box 34, Folder 17-19)
      The Citizens Advisory Committee (CAC) of the New York - New Jersey Harbor Estuary Program was formed to provide public input to program decision-making on behalf of the stakeholders in the Hudson/Raritan Estuary and the NY Bight.
    - Ocean & Coastal Management, 1993 (Offsite-box 34, Folder 20)
    - Optimizing Recycling in All the Neighborhoods in New York City, 2004 March (Offsite-box 34, Folder 21)
    - Priority Acquisition & Restoration Sites (1 of 2), 2001 (Offsite-box 34, Folder 22)
    - Priority Acquisition & Restoration Sites (2 of 2). Oversize, 2001 (Folder OS-Large, Folder 1)
      File contains a map of the priority acquisition and restoration sites of the New York/New Jersey Harbor Estuary.
    - Proposal by NY/NJ Poseidon Terminal Corporation, 1998 July (Offsite-box 34, Folder 23)
    - Proposal for an Urban Estuarine Research Reserve for the NY/NJ Harbor Estuary, 1990-1993 (Offsite-box 34, Folder 24)
    - Section 106, 1998 (Offsite-box 34, Folder 25)
    - The State of The City's Waters, 1994 (Offsite-box 34, Folder 26)
    - Successes and Challenges: Highlights of Program Accomplishments and Challenges for the Future, 2001 February (Offsite-box 34, Folder 27)
    - Summary of the Comprehensive Conversation & Management Plan, 1995-1996 (Offsite-box 34, Folder 28)
    - Wildlife Habitats and Populations, 1991 (Offsite-box 34, Folder 29)
    - Working Draft: Proposed Site Selection and Management Criteria for use of Sub-Aqueous Borrow Pits for Disposal of Dredged Material from the Port of New York and New Jersey, 1986 (Offsite-box 35, Folder 1)
  - Subseries IV.F. Manhattan Community Board #9 (MCB9), 1981-1992
    Subseries IV.F. consists of correspondence, minutes, reports, financial records, and documentation related to the development of the by-laws of Manhattan Community Board #9 (MCB9). The purpose of MCB9 is to ensure that New York City services are accessible to residents, organizations, and institutions in the neighborhoods of Hamilton Heights, Manhattanville, Morningside Heights, and West Harlem. MCB9 has several committees responsible for researching issues, developing goals, planning activities, and conducting public hearings for their respective subject area. Eugenia Flatow was chair of the Public Services Committee, which no longer exists.
    - Budget Priorities (2 Folders), 1987-1992 (Offsite-box 35, Folder 2-3)
    - By-laws (3 Folders), 1986-1990 (Offsite-box 35, Folder 4-6)
    - City-owned Property Report, 1989 (Offsite-box 35, Folder 7)
    - Columbia University Center for Engineering and Physical Science Research Civic Project, 1988 (Offsite-box 35, Folder 8)
    - Community Participation and Urban Planning: A Fragile Relationship, 1989 (Offsite-box 35, Folder 9)
    - A Comprehensive Plan for the Development of All Vacant New York City Owned Residential Properties (Land and Buildings) Within Community Board Nine/Manhattan, 1989 (Offsite-box 35, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1988-1990 (Offsite-box 35, Folder 11)
    - District Manger's Reports, 1989-1990 (Offsite-box 35, Folder 12)
    - GameTime, Park & Playground Equipment, 1990 (Offsite-box 35, Folder 13)
    - Hoboken Ferry, 1989 June (Offsite-box 35, Folder 14)
    - Inventory of Residential Social Services Facilities for Special Populations, 1988-1989 (Offsite-box 35, Folder 15)
    - Meeting Minutes (2 Folders), 1987-1990 (Offsite-box 35, Folder 16-17)
    - Memorandum of Understanding between The Lower East Side Community Board No.3 and the City of New York, Department of Housing Preservation and Development, undated (Offsite-box 35, Folder 18)
    - New York City's Uniform Land Use Review Procedure (ULURP), 1981 (Offsite-box 35, Folder 19)
    - The Origin and Significance of the Effects of the North River Water Pollution Control (Sewage Treatment) Facility on Neighborhood Air Quality, 1987 (Offsite-box 35, Folder 20)
    - Report of Activities, 1989-1990 (Offsite-box 35, Folder 21)
    - Riverbank State Park: Proposed Value Engineering Modifications, 1989 (Offsite-box 35, Folder 22)
    - Riverside Drive and Park Extension (1 of 2), 1987 (Offsite-box 35, Folder 23)
    - Riverside Drive and Park Extension (2 of 2). Oversize, 1987 (Folder OS-Large, Folder 1)
      One poster advertising the 50th-anniversary celebration of the expansion of Riverside Park.
    - Summary of Comprehensive Plan for Community Board Nine, 1989 (Offsite-box 35, Folder 24)
    - Treasurer's Report, 1989-1990 (Offsite-box 35, Folder 25)
  - Subseries IV.G. Jamaica Bay Task Force (JBTF), 1981-2006
    Subseries IV.G. contains correspondence, reports, maps, publications, and other materials related to Jamaica Bay and the Jamaica Bay Task Force. The Jamaica Bay Task Force (JBTF) was established in 1983 at the end of the first Jamaica Bay Conference held at Queens College. The JBTF served as a conduit of information among several different public and private organizations. One of these organizations was The National Harbor Estuary Program (HEP), in which Flatow played a prominent role. The HEP was a major forum (through its Citizens' Advisory Committee and committee structure) to investigate issues associated with Jamaica Bay.
    - American Littoral Society, Jamaica Bay Guardian, 2006 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 1)
    - Averne, circa 1990 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 2)
    - Benthos Study (2 Folders), 1984 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 3-4)
    - Blue Ribbon Panel (3 Folders), 2000-2001 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 5-7)
    - Council Hearing on Jamaica Bay, 1992 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 8)
    - Jamaica Bay, 1984-1989 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 9)
    - Jamaica Bay and Kennedy Airport, circa 1971 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 10)
    - Jamaica Bay Environmental Conference, 1984 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 11)
    - Jamaica Bay History, 1978-2002, bulk 1978-1984 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 12)
    - Jamaica Bay Reports, 1999-2003 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 13)
    - Jamaica Bay Task Force History, circa 1989-2001 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 14)
    - Jamaica Bay Task Force Maps, 1990-1993 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 15)
    - Jamaica Bay Task Force Minutes, 1981, 1992-1998 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 16)
    - Jamaica Bay Task Force, Miscellaneous (2 Folders), 1984-1992 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 17-18)
    - Jamaica Bay/ Rockaways Development, 1980-2000 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 19)
    - Public Hearing on Jamaica Bay Marine and Environmental Issues, 2003 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 20)
  - Subseries IV.H. The City Club of New York, 1986-2008 (bulk 1991-2005)
    The City Club of New York is an independent, not-for-profit organization with a long history of civic action for government reform and raising issues that impact the lives of the people of New York City. The Club serves as a nonpartisan "watchdog" of the New York City government, working to make it more effective, honest, ethical, and responsive to its citizens. Flatow was heavily involved in this organization, serving as Trustee, Treasurer, and Chair of its Environmental Committee. Subseries IV.H. primarily contains budgetary, banking, and tax documentation, which reflect her role as Treasurer. There is also a substantial amount of material regarding the NYC Watershed Council -- a coalition of 24 major civic, scientific, environmental, housing, and business groups committed to guaranteeing a safe and plentiful water supply for millions of users.
    - Administrative, 1999-2003 (Offsite-box 36, Folder 22)
    - Annual Reports, 1992-1997 (Offsite-box 36, Folder 23)
    - Bank Statements (4 Folders), 2003-2005, 2008 (Offsite-box 36, Folder 24-27)
    - Bank Statements (2 Folders), 2003-2005, 2008 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 1-2)
    - Bills (2 Folders), 2003-2005 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 3-4)
    - City Club Board, 2003-2005 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 5)
    - City Club Minutes, 1996-2004 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 6)
    - City Club, Miscellaneous (3 Folders), 1999-2006 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 7-9)
    - Credit Card Statements, 2002 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 10)
    - Deposits, 2004 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 11)
    - Drinking Water, 1996 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 12)
    - Earthling Awards (2 Folders), 1992-1995 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 13-14)
    - Expense, 2004 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 15)
    - Expert Panel - Safety, 1995 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 16)
    - Global Payments (2 Folders), 2002-2005 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 17-18)
    - Income (3 Folders), 2003-2004 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 19-21)
    - Letterhead, undated (Offsite-box 37, Folder 22)
    - Making New York City's Term Limits Law Work (briefing book), 2001 December (Offsite-box 37, Folder 23)
    - Meetings (2 Folders), 2004 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 24-25)
    - Membership, 2004-2005 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 26)
    - NYC Watershed Council (2 Folders), 1994-2002 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 27-28)
    - NYC Watershed Financials, 2001-2004 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 29)
    - NYC Watershed Rules, 1994-1995 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 30)
    - Tax Documents ("Waste"), 2004-2005 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 31)
    - Tax Reports, 2004 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 32)
    - Term Limits, 2004 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 33)
    - Testimony, 1994-1997 (Offsite-box 38, Folder 1)
    - Treasurer Reports (2 Folders), 2004 (Offsite-box 38, Folder 2-3)
    - Water Supply, 1986-1998 (Offsite-box 38, Folder 4)
    - Watershed, 1991-2000 (Offsite-box 38, Folder 5)
  - Subseries IV.I. New York City Soil and Water Conservation District, 1994-2007
    The NYC Soil and Water Conservation District (NYCSWCD) was formed in 1991 to promote the conservation of soil and water through working with citizens, non-governmental organizations, elected officials, and sister agencies. It evolved into an agency that facilitates projects to foster clean water and biodiversity, control and prevent soil erosion and sediment damage, and educate the youth on urban conservation techniques. Eugenia Flatow was a long-time chair of the Board and one of the individuals who advocated for the establishment of the soil and water conservation district. Subseries IV.I. largely consists of correspondence regarding all aspects of NYCSWCD activity, including research, event planning, soil surveys, conservation work, and environmental education for people of all ages. For images of NYCSWCD events, see Series VII. Photographs.
    - Act Locally: Metro Biodiversity in the Hands of Volunteers (conference proceedings), 1999 January (Offsite-box 38, Folder 6)
    - Bloomingdale Park, 1999-2002 (Offsite-box 38, Folder 7)
    - Contact Lists (3 Folders), 2002 (Offsite-box 38, Folder 8-10)
    - Correspondence (11 Folders), 1994-2007 (Offsite-box 38, Folder 11-21)
    - Living with Nature (conference), 2006 October (Offsite-box 38, Folder 22)
    - NYC Department of Environmental Protection (DEP) Contracts and Reports (3 Folders), 2000-2002 (Offsite-box 38, Folder 23-25)
    - NYC Wholesale Farmers' Market (NYC WFM) Advisory Committee, circa 2003-2007 (Offsite-box 38, Folder 26)
    - Wonderful Watersheds: A Teacher's Guide, 2005 (Offsite-box 38, Folder 27)
    - Contact Cards, undated (Offsite-box 39)
- Series V. Personal Files, 1940-2007
  Series V contains material related to Eugenia Flatow's time in graduate school, her campaign for councilman-at-large, and her participation in The College of New Rochelle (CNR) alumni community. While there is not much information regarding Flatow's personal life in the collection, the records in this series offer a glimpse into her early political ideology and areas of interest.
  Materials in this series are arranged in the order they arrived in.
  - Political Campaign (2 Folders), 1963-1965 (Offsite-box 39, Folder 1-2)
    The file contains documentation from Flatow's run for Manhattan Councilman-at-large in the mid-1960s. There are also records of her participation in the Democratic party, particularly the Riverside Democrats.
  - Columbia - Genie's Masters, 1946-1951, 1974-1975 (Offsite-box 39, Folder 3)
  - The College of New Rochelle (2 Folders), 1940-1986 (Offsite-box 39, Folder 4-5)
  - Maps, undated (Offsite-box 39, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 2003-2007 (Offsite-box 39, Folder 7)
- Series VI. Photographs and Digital Media, 1990s-2000s
  Series VI is organized in two subseries:
  Subseries VI.A. Photographs, circa 1990s-2000s
  Subseries VI.B. Digital Media, 2000-2003
  Series VI contains photographs and digital media of events Eugenia Flatow attended and was likely instrumental in planning. Most of these events were coordinated by the New York City Soil and Water Conservation District (NYCSWCD), and the photos feature school children participating in activities in natural resource areas all over New York City. The digital media in this series predominately documents activities of the NYCSWCD through photographs and a Microsoft Access database.
  - Subseries VI.A. Photographs, circa 1990s-2000s
    Subseries VI.A. largely consists of photographs of events organized by the New York City Soil and Water Conservation District (NYCSWCD), particularly the Envirothon – a national environmental science competition for high school students. Photographs of this event exhibit New York City students from all five boroughs engaging with hands-on activities in natural resource areas such as Alley Pond and Central Park. Other photographs in this subseries show a boat trip around Manhattan on a New York Water Taxi, a NYCSWCD event held at PS 28, and the City Club's annual Earthling Awards.
    - Envirothon Central Park (2 Albums), circa 2000s (Offsite-box 40, Album 1-2)
    - Envirothon Alley Pond (2 Albums), circa 2000s (Offsite-box 40, Album 3-4)
    - Envirothon, Council Chamber Prize Ceremony (2 Albums), circa 2000s (Offsite-box 40, Album 5-6)
    - NYCSWCD H/H Photos, 2003 (Offsite-box 40, Album 7)
    - HEP Eco II, 2001 June (Offsite-box 40, Album 8)
    - H/H PS 28, 2003 (Offsite-box 40, Album 9)
    - NYCSWCD Events, circa 2000-2003 (Offsite-box 40, Album 10)
    - Conference at the American Museum of Natural History, circa 1990s-2000s (Offsite-box 40, Album 11)
    - Envirothon Alley Pond, circa 1990s-2000s (Offsite-box 40, Folder 1)
    - Earthling Awards (3 Envelopes), circa 1992-1995 (Offsite-box 40, Folder 2-4)
    - Boat Trip Around Manhattan, circa 1990s (Offsite-box 40, Folder 5)
    - Envirothon '98 Prospect Park, 1998 (Offsite-box 40, Folder 6)
    - Envirothon 2000 (Offsite-box 40, Folder 7)
      Includes negatives.
    - New York Restoration Project/ High Bridge, 1998 (Offsite-box 40, Folder 8)
    - H/H PS28 (contact sheets), 2003 (Offsite-box 40, Folder 9)
      This file contains contact sheets for the photos in the H/H PS28 Spring 03 photo album. The envelopes were labeled #1 and #4 by Flatow. There are no envelopes labeled #2 or #3.
    - NACD Executive Committee Meeting (negatives), 2002 August (Offsite-box 40, Folder 10)
    - Envirothon Awards Ceremony, 2000 (Offsite-box 40, Folder 11)
    - City Island, 2000 August (Offsite-box 40, Folder 12)
    - Student Field Trip, circa 1990s-2000s (Offsite-box 40, Folder 13)
    - East Coast Greenway Biking Event, circa 1990s-2000s (Offsite-box 40, Folder 14)
    - Soil Testing, circa 1990s-2000s (Offsite-box 40, Folder 15)
    - NOSC Bronx Tour (slides), circa 1990s-2000s (Offsite-box 40, Folder 16)
    - Envirothon 2002 (Offsite-box 40, Folder 17)
    - New York City Skyline, circa 2000 (Offsite-box 40, Folder 18)
  - Subseries VI.B. Digital Media, 2000-2003
    Subseries VI.B. consists of 10 CDs containing 610 MB (449 files) of photographs and a Microsoft Access database for the New York City Soil and Water Conservation District (NYCSWCD). The bulk of these files are digital versions of the photographs contained in Subseries VI.A. Photographs. The photos mostly depict NYCSWCD events, such as the Envirothon, but also include images of natural resource areas in Brooklyn, the Bronx, Manhattan, Queens, and Staten Island. The database contains information relevant to an unidentified conference, including preliminary panel information and contact lists. A manifest of the digital files is available from the reference librarian on request.
    Each of the entries in the container list represents one CD and the title is based on the labeling from the physical CD. Each CD contains many individual files. Some of these files may not be accessible due to file corruption or because the library does not have the proprietary software necessary.
    The first 10 entries represent one CD and the title is based on the labeling from the physical CD. The digital files from each CD may be requested. The last entry represents the physical CDs, which can be requested to view but are restricted from being used.
    - Dave Lutz Photos, 2002 July (Digital-folder MS 3175)
    - Envirothon Photos, 2003 (Digital-folder MS 3175)
    - Flotilla, 2002 (Digital-folder MS 3175)
    - NACD Executive Committee Meeting (2 CDs), 2002 August (Digital-folder MS 3175)
    - Natural Resource Area Pictures, 2000-2003 (Digital-folder MS 3175)
    - NYC Soil Survey, 2002 (Digital-folder MS 3175)
    - NYCSWCD H/H Photos, 2003 (Digital-folder MS 3175)
    - Soils Graphics, 2000 (Digital-folder MS 3175)
    - SWCD Database, 2003 January (Digital-folder MS 3175)
    - 10 CDs (RESTRICTED), 2000-2003 (Offsite-box 40, Disk 1-10)